A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Vice President for Assets, Office Files of Dr. Melvin L Oliver FA508
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Vice President for Assets, Office Files of Dr. Melvin L Oliver
1982-2009 (Bulk 1992-2004)
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA508
4 Cubic Feet
The Asset Building and Community Development Program was established in October 1996 as part of a Foundation-wide program reorganization. The new program supported the work of a range of groups and individuals seeking to build the assets and capacities of poor communities through community-based activities, research, policy analysis, and advocacy. In 2009, the Asset Building and Community Development Program became the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program. Dr. Melvin L. Oliver joined the Ford Foundation in 1996. He served as the Foundation's first Vice President for Asset Building and Community Development and worked on issues relating to poverty, community economic development, and reproductive health. The Office Files of Melvin L. Oliver document his professional activities as Vice President of the Assets Program between 1996 and 2009. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence concerning such subjects as ongoing grant activity, potential grantees, and Foundation policy, and briefing books from meetings, conferences, and field visits. A couple of files pertaining to Dr. Oliver's pre-Ford research and writing in Sociology during the 1980s can also be found in the collection.
(10 Hollinger document boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment. Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Biographical Note
Dr. Melvin L. Oliver was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania in 1950. He received an undergraduate degree from William Penn College in Iowa (1972) and was awarded an M.A. (1974) and a PhD (1977) in Sociology from Washington University in St. Louis. In 1978, he joined the faculty of the University of California Los Angeles, where he worked for the next 17 years. He became known for his work in Sociology, receiving such honors as a fellowship grant from the Ford Foundation in 1982 and the title of “California Professor of the Year” from the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching in 1994.
Dr. Oliver joined the Ford Foundation in 1996. He served as the Foundation’s first Vice President for Asset Building and Community Development and worked on issues relating to poverty, community economic development, and reproductive health. In 2004, he returned to academia, accepting an appointment as SAGE Sara Miller McCune Dean of Social Sciences and Professor of Sociology at the University of California Santa Barbara.
Organizational History
The Asset Building and Community Development Program was established in October 1996 as part of the Foundation-wide program reorganization in the 1997 fiscal year. It took over existing Foundation programs in Urban Poverty, Rural Poverty and Resources, Reproductive Health and Population, and Program-Related Investments. The Assets Program had three program units: Economic Development; Community and Resource Development; and Human Development and Reproductive Health. In 2009, the Asset Building and Community Development Program became the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program.
Arrangement
Arranged into 3 series.
Scope and Content Note
The Office Files of Dr. Melvin L. Oliver, a well-known sociologist, document his professional activities between 1982 and 2009. The bulk of files pertain to his tenure as Vice President of the Assets Program at the Ford Foundation.
Separated Materials
A photograph of Dr. Oliver and a fellow Ford Foundation staff member at the Great Wall of China has been transferred to the Trustees and Staff Photo Collection.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access note
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Date spans of this collection range from 1982-2009. As such, some of the material is closed to scholarly access until the applicable records are more than ten years old. Material will be open for research as records reach the ten year threshold, 2014-2020.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Ford Foundation
- Correspondence, 1996-2002; I (Box not specified)
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of Mr. Oliver's incoming and outgoing correspondence and memoranda that Dr. Oliver arranged chronologically by year, and within years, alphabetically by correspondent. Dr. Oliver's separation of external correspondence from internal Ford Foundation memoranda was maintained. Subjects of correspondence include ongoing grant actions, potential grantees, Foundation policy, and other subjects. The files also contain copies of newspaper and magazine articles retained by Dr. Oliver for discussion or reference.
  - Chron File (1 of 18): A-F, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chron File (2 of 18): G-L, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chron File (3 of 18): M-Q, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chron File (4 of 18): S-Z, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chron File (5 of 18): Memoranda, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chron File (6 of 18): A-D, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chron File (7 of 18): E-H, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chron File (8 of 18): I-Z, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chron File (9 of 18): Memoranda, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chron File (10 of 18): A-L, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chron File (11 of 18): M-Z, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chron File (12 of 18): Memoranda, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chron File (13 of 18): A-Z, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chron File (14 of 18): Memoranda, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chron File (15 of 18): A-Z, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chron File (16 of 18): Memoranda, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Chron File (17 of 18): A-Z, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chron File (18 of 18): A-Z, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - DeGiovanni, Frank -- Correspondence re: PRIs, 1997-2009 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Some of the records in this file are restricted because they are less than 10 years old. The restricted items have been segregated and are inaccessible. The file is open to research, and physical removal of the segregated material is not necessary.
    Date Restricted Material -- Contains records less than 10 years old -- Pertinent records are Open to scholarly research in 2017, 2018, and 2020.
- Meetings, Conferences and Visits, 1991-2004; II (Box not specified)
  As Vice President, Dr. Oliver traveled extensively, visiting grantee locations, attending conferences, and meeting with other Foundation staff members. This series is comprised of the briefing books and other materials he retained from his travels.
  - Poverty and Race Research Action Council (PRRAC) Board Meeting, Washington D.C., Dec 16, 1996 -- Agenda, Notes, Correspondence, 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Natural Resources Management Program Officer Consultation, Napa Valley, CA, Jun 9-11, 1996 -- Memoranda, Agenda, Program Descriptions, Notes, Discussion Papers, Apr-Jun 1996 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Asset Program Retreat -- Agenda, Notes, Background, May 20-Jul 31, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Community Development Collaborative Partnership Conference -- Agenda, Memoranda, Jun 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Development Finance Affinity Group Meeting, Positano, Italy, Nov 4-8, 1996 -- Meeting Book, Memoranda, Sep-Nov 1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mexico City Field Office Visit -- Itinerary, Agenda, Meeting Book (1 of 2), Jan 2-10, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mexico City Field Office Visit -- Background (2 of 2), Jan 2-10, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Madras and New Delhi, India -- Itinerary, Notes, Conference Program, Background Papers (1 of 3), Jan 31-Feb 8, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Madras and New Delhi, India -- Background Papers (2 of 3), Jan 31-Feb 8, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Madras and New Delhi, India -- Ford Program Office Meeting Book (3 of 3), Jan 31-Feb 8, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Trustees Tour of Virginia's Eastern Shore, Northampton County, Virginia, Mar 1997 -- Agenda, Background, Memoranda, Grant Recommendations, 1991-1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reproductive Health Worldwide Affinity Group Meeting, Marrakesh, Morocco, Jun 14-19, 1997, Dec 1996-Jun 1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - National Research Council Conference of Ford Fellows, Washington D.C., Oct 17, 1997, Dec 20, 1996-Nov 5, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Natural Resources Affinity Group Meeting, Istanbul, Turkey, Nov 12-16, 1997, Nov-Dec 1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Brookings Institution Meeting on Community Development Corporations (CDCs), Jan 1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Beijing Field Office Visit -- Agenda and Background, Mar 1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Rural Community College Initiative (RCCI) Road Trip, May 11-13, 1998 -- Itinerary, Background, Correspondence, May-Jul 1998 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Corporation for Enterprise Development (CFED) Ideas in Development Conference, Washington D.C., Jun 24, 1999, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Visit to the World Bank, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - National Center of Strategic Nonprofit Planning and Community Leadership (NPLC) and National Minority AIDS Council (NMAC) Site Visits, Mar 13, 2001, 1998-2001 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Children's Defense Fund National Symposium on Arts and Scholarship, Clinton, TN, Mar 19-21, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - New School University -- Notes, PowerPoint, Email, Conference Information, Apr 30, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - All Africa Program Officers and Representatives Meeting, Zanzibar (1 of 2), Aug 25-Sep 1, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - All Africa Program Officers and Representatives Meeting, Zanzibar (2 of 2), Aug 25-Sep 1, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Reproductive Health Affinity Group Annual Meeting, Bahia, Brazil, Oct 9-14, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Ten Point Coalition Visit, Oct 27, 1999, Oct 5-Nov 28, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Development Finance Affinity Group Meeting, London, UK -- Agenda, Notes, PowerPoint, Background, Nov 7-10, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Meeting, Jun 27-29, 2000, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Natural Assets Conference -- Agenda, Meeting Book, Background (1 of 2), Jan 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Natural Assets Conference -- Meeting Book (2 of 2), Jan 2000 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Worldwide Meeting on Youth Involvement, Costa Rica -- Workshop Information (1 of 3), Jan 4-7, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Worldwide Meeting on Youth Involvement, Costa Rica -- Country Profiles A-Q (2 of 3), Jan 4-7, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Worldwide Meeting on Youth Involvement, Costa Rica -- Country Profiles R-Z (3 of 3), Jan 4-7, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Environmental and Development Affinity Group (EDAG) Meeting, Mactan, Philippines -- Agenda Book with Background, Papers, Memoranda (1 of 2), Feb 14-18, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Environmental and Development Affinity Group (EDAG) Meeting, Mactan, Philippines -- Itinerary, PowerPoint, Notes, Case Study (2 of 2), Feb 14-18, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Moscow Field Office Visit (1 of 2), Mar 2000 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Moscow Field Office Visit (2 of 2), Mar 2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Africa and Middle East Rep RAP, Jerusalem -- Briefing Book, Oct 1-6, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Building Broader Women's Health/Reproductive Healthcare Coalitions in the States" (report) by Terry McGovern, Oct 24, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Chicago/Cleveland Shorebank Site Visits and Cleveland Saves Meeting, Nov 30-Dec 4, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Federation of Southern Cooperative/Land Assistance Fund -- Correspondence and memoranda re: grantee, background, 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Reproductive Health Affinity Group Annual Meeting, Cape Town, South Africa, Jan 18-22, 2002, 2000-2002 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Vietnam Visit, Jan 8-13, 2001 -- Itinerary, Notes, Memoranda (1 of 3), 2000-2001 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam Visit, Jan 8-13, 2001 -- Briefing Book (2 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Vietnam Visit, Jan 8-13, 2001 -- Briefing Book (3 of 3) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Youth Service Workshop, Costa Rica, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Cairo Field Office Visit, Mar 2001 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Environmental and Development Affinity Group (EDAG) Meeting, Cape Town, South Africa, Jan 21-25, 2002 -- Program, Schedule, Notes, Email, Oct 18, 2001 - Jan 21, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "Reflections on The Ford Foundation's Role in Building a Global Field of Development Finance and Economic Security" (separated report) by Frank F. DeGiovanni, Feb 20, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Affinity Group on Development Finance and Economic Security Meeting, Beijing, China -- Meeting Book, Agenda, Reports, Background, Feb 26-Mar 3, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Visit to Mexico -- Meeting Book, Agenda, RGAs, May 11-19, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Latin America Regional Program -- Annotated Agenda, Background, Oct 2002 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Asia Representatives' Meeting, Hanoi, Vietnam -- Meeting Book, Dec 9-11, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - All Africa Program Staff Meeting, Sep 17-20, 2002 -- Agenda, Objectives, Background, Briefing Book, 2002-2003 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Corporate Involvement Initiative (CII) Convening, Jun 2-4, 2003 -- Correspondence, Agenda, Background, Mar 24-Jun 2, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Special Initiative on Africa: Senegal (1 of 2), Aug 2004 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Special Initiative on Africa: Senegal (2 of 2), Aug 2004 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Research and Writing, 1982-1988; III (Box not specified)
  This series consists of two folders. Both pre-date Dr. Oliver’s tenure at the Foundation. One contains information retained by Dr. Oliver about his Ford Foundation-funded postdoctoral fellowship administered by the National Science Foundation. The other is an undated paper from the early 1980s containing Dr. Oliver’s views on affirmative action.
  - "Is Affirmative Action Necessary? One Sociologist's Viewpoint" by Melvin L. Oliver, early 1980s (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - National Science Foundation Postdoctoral Fellowship, 1982-1988 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- APPENDIX A: Reports
  - AGDF, Update on the Development Finance Industry - Where Are the Gaps that the GI/IF Might Fill? A Report for the Ford Foundation, 2002 (Report 19527)
  - Aidoo, Akwasi, Maputo Trip Report: SIA Workshop on Peace and Conflicts in Africa, 2002 (Report 19532)
  - DeGiovanni, Frank F., Reflections on the Ford Foundation's Role in Building a Global Field of Development Finance and Economic Security, 2002 (Report 19533)
  - Dempers, Im Uhuru, Namibia Country Paper: Land Reform and Transition in Namibia, 2001 (Report 19540)
  - Faulhaber, Ingrid, Development Finance: A Background Paper on the State of the Field, 2001 (Report 19528)
  - Greenberg, Stephen, Land Reform and Transition in South Africa, 2002 (Report 19541)
  - La Vina, Antonio G. M., The State of Community Based Forest Management in the Philippines and the Role of Local Governments, 1999 (Report 19526)
    - Hlatshwayo, Zakes, Land Reform Processes in South Africa, 2002 (Report 19539)
  - Magome, Hector, South African National Parks: Land Acquisition Strategy, Land Claims and Transfrontier Conservation Areas, 2002 (Report 19536)
  - Miller, Thomas F., The Ford Foundation's Global Role in Advancing Development Finance and Economic Security, 2001 (Report 19529)
  - Moyo, Sam, Land Reform and Transition in Zimbabwe (draft), 2002 (Report 19542)
  - Songelwa, N. C., Gender, Environment and Sustainable Development: Reflections from Rural Voices, 2002 (Report 19538)
  - Affinity Group on Development Finance: 1999-2000 Operating Plan and Project Status: Second Draft (Report 19554)
  - Africa Philanthropy Initiative (API): First Year Progress Report, 1999 (Report 19530)
  - A Scan of the Assets Program's Affinity Groups, 1999 (Report 19524)
  - An Overview of Land Claims in Protected Areas in South Africa, 2002 (Report 19537)
  - Building Broader Women's Health/Reproductive Healthcare Coalitions in the States: A Look at Idaho, Texas and Florida: An Open Society Institute Initiative, 2000 (Report 19523)
  - Building Natural Assets and Wealth to Reduce Poverty: Concepts and Potential Applications in the United States, 2000 (Report 19543)
  - Can the Natural Assets of Cities Help Address Urban Poverty?, 2000 (Report 19544)
  - Corporate Involvement Initiative: Frameworks and Findings from the Learning Agenda (draft), 2003 (Report 19545)
    This material is closed to scholarly access until the applicable records are more than ten years old. Material will be open for research as records reach the ten year threshold, 2013.
  - The Informal Solid Waste Sector in Egypt: Prospects for Formalization, 2001 (Report 19549)
  - Institutions and Uncertainty: New Directions in Natural Resource Management (draft), 1999 (Report 19525)
  - Interim Report to the Affinity Group on Development Finance: Development Finance Institutions, Small and Medium Sized Enterprises and Low-Income Impacts (draft), 1999 (Report 19553)
  - Investing in Micro-Insurance: Briefing Paper, 1999 (Box # 019556)
  - Low-Cost Bank Accounts and the EITC: How Financial Institutions Can Reach the Unbanked and Facilitate Savings (draft), 2000 (Report 19546)
  - Moving Toward Inclusion: A Proposed Approach for a Discussion of Strategy at Commonweal, 2000 (Report 19547)
  - On-Time Grantmaking: Task Force Report #2, 2002 (Report 19531)
  - The Persistence of Poverty in a Changing World, 2001 (Report 19550)
  - Rapportuer's Notes on Meeting with Representatives of U.S. Based International Organizations to Discuss the Reproductive Health and Population Program's External Review Team Report, March 27, 1997 (Report 19551)
  - Rapportuer's Notes on Meeting with Representatives of U.S. Based International Organizations to Discuss the Reproductive Health and Population Program's External Review Team Report, April 15, 1997 (Box # 019552)
  - Room for Hope: Tenure Security for Farm Workers?, 2001 (Report 19535)
  - Scan of Opportunities for the Ford Foundation's Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative, 2000 (Report 19548)
  - To Run is Not to Arrive: What Hope for Transboundary Natural Resources Management in Southern Africa?, 2001 (Report 19534)
  - Who Owns Us? A Discussion Paper on Key Dimensions of Ownership and Governance in Evolving Community Development Finance Institutions, 1999 (Report 19555)